So today's דף Daf is מ"א Mem-Aleph 41. We pick up at
the bottom of מ' עמוד ב' Mem Amud Bet and we're dealing
with a number of statements in the name of שמואל Shmuel about
what are the requirements for like a מודה במקצת Modeh B'miktzas and
if somebody demands חיטים chitim and שעורים se'orim and only admits to
the שעורים, se'orim, is that considered ממין הטענה Mimin HaTa'ana or not
ממין הטענה? Mimin HaTa'ana? Okay, and now we pick up with אמר
רב ענן אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Anan Amar Shmuel. It is about,
oh, I don't know, about a good 20 lines before the bottom.
Line starts with the word רב ענן. Rav Anan. It's roughly across
from the תוספות Tosafos וחדא. Vachada. So אמר רב ענן אמר שמואל
טענו חיטים וקדם והודה לו בשעורים. Amar Rav Anan Amar Shmuel, Tano
Chitim Vekodam Vehodo Lo Bese'orim. So this guy said, you owe me
wheat, and he was gonna say and barley. Okay? That was like,
you know, and the guy said, no, I don't owe you wheat,
I owe you barley. So this is assuming שמואל's Shmuel earlier statement
that had he said wheat and barley and the guy admitted to
barley, that would have been a מודה במקצת, Modeh B'miktzas, it would
have been ממין הטענה, Mimin HaTa'ana, it would have been of the
same type of the claim and he would have had to take
a שבועה. shvua. But if the guy didn't get the words 'and
barley' out, the guy just said you owe me wheat and he
said, no, I owe you barley, so then he became a כופר
הכל, Kofer Hakol, right? Or not a כופר הכל, Kofer Hakol, whatever,
anyway it was טענו חיטים והודה לו בשעורים. Tano Chitim Vehodo Lo
Bese'orim. He didn't admit to anything that was part of the claim
and therefore he's totally, you know, he would be totally exempt from
the שבועה. shvua. How would we frame that? Would we look at
what the guy was going to claim and then this person who
responded is a מודה במקצת? Modeh B'miktzas? Or do we say at
the end of the day the guy just said wheat and he
responded barley and therefore he doesn't take a שבועה? shvua?
Yeah, they don't know what he was going to say. You don't
know if it was barley, could've been whatever.
From the context, we're going, that's true, but we're assuming a case
that we know that that was true in the context. Okay, so
אם כמערים חייב ואם במתכוון פטור. Im Kimarim Chayav Ve'im B'miskaven Patur.
If he's doing it as a scheme, like he, you know, then,
you know, and he knew that the guy was going to say
barley and he was doing this to prevent the guy from saying
barley, then he has to take a שבועה. shvua. שבועה דרבנן? shvua
d'Rabbanan? Well, so that's not clear. Hold on. And but if it's
במתכוון, b'miskaven, meaning if it's just like, no, like he was being
innocent and he heard wheat and he said no, barley, then he's
exempt. So of course the question is like where do we, how
do we obligate him? Like what technically is his דאורייתא d'Oraisa obligation?
So it could be it's דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, like technically you're out of
it but
rabbinically if you manipulated the situation, we're going to impose it on
you. It could also be that no, we frame the question about
what was the טענה ta'ana is not necessarily the question of what
came out of this guy's mouth, meaning if you knew the guy
was going to say barley and you essentially were responding to that
even though he didn't yet say those words, then the טענה ta'ana
did include barley. You know, so that could be part of the
question, right? What do you define as being part of the טענה
ta'ana might have to do with the context. So that's another way
of understanding that. Anyway, so now we continue. Okay, ואמר רב ענן
אמר שמואל טענו שני מחטים והודה לו באחת מהן חייב. Ve'amar Rav
Anan Amar Shmuel, Tano Shenei Machtim Vehodo Lo B'achas Mehen Chayav. So
we did, we discussed this before although now we're spelling it out,
that the idea is כלים keilim means that if it's a vessel
that's being demanded for the מודה במקצת, Modeh B'miktzas, two vessels and
you admit to one, it does not have to be a claim
worth שתי כסף, shte kessef, you know, two מעה ma'ah like we've
been calling that 20 bucks. It's enough that it's even a vessel
even worth almost nothing, although תוספות Tosafos says it does have to
be worth a פרוטה. pruta. That's the idea of חשוב. chashuv. Okay,
according to תוספות Tosafos each needle has to be worth a פרוטה.
pruta. טענו שני מחטים והודה לו באחת מהן, Tano Shenei Machtim Vehodo
Lo B'achas Mehen, so two needles and he admitted to one of
them, חייב. chayav. לפיכך יצאו כלים למה שהן. Lefikach Yatzo Keilim Lemah
Shehen. That's why
כלים keilim are treated separately as money because it's whatever they are,
meaning regardless of their market value. Again, תוספות Tosafos inserts that they
have to be worth at least a פרוטה pruta each, but שני
כלים shenei keilim is enough. Okay, אמר רב פפא טענו כלים ופרוטה
והודה בכלים וכפר בפרוטה פטור. Amar Rav Pappa, Tano Keilim Uperuta Vehodo
B'keilim Vekhafar B'peruta Patur. Let's say he said you owe me, you
know, two needles and a פרוטה, pruta, and he admitted, yes I
owe you the needles but I don't owe you the פרוטה, pruta,
then you are exempt. Okay, הודה בפרוטה וכפר בכלים חייב. Hodo B'peruta
Vekhafar B'keilim Chayav. Yes I owe you a פרוטה pruta and I
don't owe you the needles, חייב. chayav. Now what is the logic
behind this?
So the גמרא gemara spells it very nicely, spells it out for
us. חדא כרב וחדא כשמואל. Chada K'Rav Vechada K'Shmuel.
One of these assumes a position of רב Rav we discussed earlier
and one assumes a position of שמואל. Shmuel. חדא כרב דאמר כפירת
טענת שתי כסף, Chada K'Rav d'amar Kefiras Ta'anas Shte Kessef,
that it's not enough that the claim be, you know, two 20
bucks, the what's being denied has to be worth 20 bucks or
has to be worth a כלי, kli, you know, if we use
the כלים keilim model. So in this case, you have two כלים
keilim and a פרוטה. pruta. Okay, you don't have, you could say
the claim was two כלים, keilim, right? So that's, you know, that's
fine. The claim was two כלים, keilim, but we also need the
denial, right? Remember according to רב Rav you need the denial to
be worth even the 20 bucks or the two כלים. keilim. So
that's what we're saying here, that everybody agrees you have a sufficient
claim. The claim was give me my two needles and my penny.
Okay, do you have a sufficient... The claim was two כלים, Kelim,
right? So that's fine. The claim was two כלים, Kelim, but we
also need the denial, right? Remember, according to רב, Rav, you need
the denial to be worth either the twenty bucks or the two
כלים. Kelim. So that's what we're saying here, that everybody agrees you
have a sufficient claim. The claim was, "Give me my two needles
and my penny." Okay, do you have a sufficient denial? So since
one of the examples here was that if he admits to the
needles and he denies to the penny, he's exempt, okay, right? That
was the case, right? What was that? הודה בכלים וכפר בפרוטה פטור,
Hodeh be-Kelim ve-kafar bi-prutah patur, that's like רב, Rav, that it's not
enough that the claim be the twenty dollars slash two כלים, Kelim,
the denial has to be twenty dollars or two כלים. Kelim. So
if you admitted to the penny and denied the two כלים, Kelim,
you had a big enough denial. But if you admitted to the
needles and denied the penny, you did not have a big enough
denial and therefore you're exempt. Okay, so that's like רב. Rav. חדא
כרב, Chada ke-Rav, let's say that again, חדא כרב, Chada ke-Rav, דאמר
כפירת טענה שתי
כסף, de-amar kfirat ta'anah shtei kessef, that you need that the denial
be two כסף kessef or two כלים. Kelim. And that's why if
you denied the כלים Kelim you're חייב, chayav, if you denied the
פרוטה prutah you're פטור. patur. Okay, וחדא כשמואל, ve-chada ke-Shmuel, one goes
like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר טענו חטים ושעורים והודה לו באחת מהם חייב.
de-amar ta'ano chitim u-se'orim ve-hodeh lo be-achat mehem chayav. If you demanded
two separate types of things and he admitted one, he's חייב. chayav.
And that's the case where if you admit to the פרוטה prutah
and deny the כלים, Kelim, so the denial is big enough, it's
two כלים. Kelim. Ah, but you know, but that's a case where
like it's two separate things, כלים Kelim and a פרוטה, prutah, and
you admitted to the פרוטה, prutah, you denied the כלים. Kelim. That's
like חטים ושעורים chitim u-se'orim and you admitted to one of them.
So that goes like שמואל, Shmuel, that's how you're חייב. chayav. Nobody
explains, or רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan argued on שמואל, Shmuel, but רב
Rav didn't argue on שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, so the conclusion of the
גמרא, Gemara, which is pretty much where we saw things going anyway,
was that it's not enough that the claim be a certain size,
the denial has to be a certain size. That's רב. Rav. That
size is either two כסף kessef or two כלים. Kelim. Okay,
I guess. No, two כלים. Kelim. It would be yes, two כלים
Kelim according to רב. Rav. So the denial has to be a
certain size. But the other thing which also made a lot of
sense is if you demand חטים ושעורים chitim u-se'orim and you concede
to שעורים, se'orim, that's considered מודה במקצת, modeh be-miktzat, even though the
thing that you are denying you didn't admit to any part of
the חטים, chitim, nevertheless that's a מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. Okay good,
so now we continue. That was a nice way of sort of
pulling together some of the earlier discussions. Alright, now we pick up
with the two dots, going back to the משנה. Mishnah. "מנה לי
בידך maneh li beyadcha, אין לך בידי" פטור. patur, Okay,
so that's a straight כופר הכל kofer ha-kol is exempt. And of
course everybody reads that and says, "Wait, wait, you're just totally off?
You don't have to do anything? You just totally deny a claim?"
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to. Let's
take a look. אמר רב נחמן, משביעין אותו שבועת היסת. Amar Rav
Nachman: Mashbi'in oto shvu'at hesset.
But we do make him swear a שבועת היסת. shvu'at hesset. There's
a question what the word היסת hesset means. Right, רש"י Rashi says
it means like seduced, like the, or like the rabbis like sort
of persuaded you to make it because really biblically you're not obligated
to make it. Okay, so they persuade you, you don't have to
say, "I
know, I know, I understand."
Anyway, it's you know, it's very very what they call like strong
arm but you can't resist.
Exactly, strong arm persuasion.
It's not exactly clear anyway what you know, what exactly the etymology
is. But a שבועת היסת shvu'at hesset is sort of like a
generic שבועה shvu'ah that the rabbis instituted. I mean, we're going to
see a certain types of שבועה דרבנן shvu'ah de-rabbanan in very specific
concrete cases which are coming up, which is a case of נשבעין
ונוטלין. nishba'in ve-notlin. That I have a claim, like you know, that
you're basically my worker and you say you haven't paid me today,
and I say I did pay you, and da da da. Anyway,
and there's something where there's a lot of very concrete evidence and
circumstances and then we let you take a שבועה shvu'ah and take
your money. Okay, that's the certain small number of rabbinic שבועות shvu'ot
of נשבעין ונוטלין. nishba'in ve-notlin. But basically, that's a very, you know,
that's like a very small number of cases in very specific circumstances.
But then there's this generic שבועה shvu'ah called שבועת היסת. shvu'at hesset.
Which pretty much is anytime sort of like, you know, we're not
exactly sure, I mean, depends we'll see in a minute the debate
about the scope. But it's pretty much a שבועה shvu'ah that you
can very readily just say, "Wait, I don't believe you, take a
שבועה, shvu'ah, שבועת היסת." shvu'at hesset. Or whatever, you need to back
that up, you know, or something. And so there's, so this is
like, becomes a very generic type of a שבועה, shvu'ah, although we're
about to see in a minute what the circumstances are. But mostly,
again, it's a שבועה shvu'ah about being exempt. You're making a claim,
it's not a מודה במקצת, modeh be-miktzat, it's not an עד אחד,
ed echad, it's not a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, technically speaking, it's
a he said he said, or whatever he said she said, or
she said she said anyway, you know, and your claim is just
believed. I say you owe me a hundred dollars, you say no,
you get to walk away. No you don't need anything to back
it up. But the rabbis say, "Wait wait, we're going to, we
need to back that up a little bit," okay, and you have
to make a שבועת היסת. shvu'at hesset. Okay, so before you walk
away. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן: Amar Rav
Nachman, משביעין אותו שבועת היסת. mashbi'in oto shvu'at hesset. Okay, you make
him take this שבועת היסת. shvu'at hesset. מאי טעמא? חזקה אין אדם
תובע אלא אם כן
יש לו עליו. Mai ta'ama? Chazakah ein adam tove'a ela im ken
yesh lo alav. Because if I say you owe me a hundred
dollars, presumably I'm not totally making it up. Meaning, if I'm going
to force a שבועה shvu'ah on this guy, right, if the rabbis
are going to say this guy the defendant has to make a
שבועה, shvu'ah, it's probably because there's some basis to suspect that maybe
he owes the money. What's the basis? You know, ראובן Reuven just
came out of nowhere and said, "You owe me a hundred dollars,"
and שמעון Shimon said, "You're crazy, I don't." So is that fair
that ראובן Reuven makes שמעון Shimon take a שבועה? shvu'ah? Yes, because
ראובן Reuven probably would not demand it if there was not some,
if there was not some basis for it. אדרבה, Adarabba, says the
גמרא, Gemara, חזקה אין אדם מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו. Chazakah ein
adam me'iz panav bifnei ba'al hovo. We could say that there's a
חזקה chazakah that a person does not have the temerity to deny
a debt and if he's saying you don't owe me anything, then
presumably he's telling the truth. No, אשתמוטי הוא דקא משתמיט ליה. Ishtamutei
hu de-ka mishtamit lei.
He's just pushing him off. Maybe he really does owe the debt,
sometimes people really do deny it fully. And then why, so how
could they do that? That's so, such ingratitude. No, they're not really
going to fully deny it, they're just saying for now they're claiming
that so that they can get the money together, okay? סבר
אדהוה ליה פרענא ליה savar ad hava lei parana lei until I
get money together then I'll pay him off. תידע, teida, you should
know this is true,
this applies to also let's say you gave me to watch two
מחטין machatin and a פרוטה. pruta.
Yeah, yeah, okay, might not be, okay. תידע, teida, דאמר רב אידי
בר אבין אמר רב חסדא, teida d'amar Rav Idi bar Avin amar
Rav Chisda, הכופר במלוה כשר לעדות, ha'kofer be'milveh kasher l'eidus, בפיקדון פסול
לעדות. be'pikadon pasul l'eidus. If somebody denies that they owed money and
then witnesses come and testify the guy was lying, he did borrow
the money, he could still be a כשר עד, kasher eid, whereas
if somebody denied that he was watching an object for
somebody and witnesses say, what are you talking about, we saw him
put it in his knapsack just a minute ago, your iPhone and
so on, so then he cannot be an עד. eid. What's the
difference? Because in the first case we say that his denial, and
it's not a denial בשבועה, be'shvuah, it was just I say where
is it and you denied it. So in one case that denial
doesn't really mean you're a real liar in the first case. It's,
I mean, it means you're just pushing me off, but it, well
you did lie, but you didn't lie with the extent of, with
the intent
of keeping something that wasn't yours. It was just a way of
pushing me off to stop nudging you for the hundred dollars I
keep in order to buy yourself some time. Whereas in the case
of an object, if you actually have my object, why are you
not giving it back? Okay, and the fact that you're saying you
don't have it when you do have it, if it got lost
or broken or whatever, we'll back to see, then maybe you're lying
in order to find it or in order to pay me back
for it, that's a different story. But if you have it in
your knapsack and you're saying you don't have it, he must be
you're intending to steal it. So it's interesting, if somebody is known
to have lied in the context of this back and forth, this
doesn't make him פסול לעדות. pasul l'eidus. Could you imagine that? Anytime
you bring testimony that somebody once lied in their lives so they
couldn't be a witness, nobody would ever be a witness. Okay, so
therefore like these types of lies that are not really with the
intent to steal
are not enough to invalidate somebody as a witness. Okay, and that's
the first case. But the second case we define it as with
the intent to steal and it does invalidate. רב חביב Rav Chaviv
now,
so therefore anyway, so based on that distinction we're saying that if
I come and say you owe me a hundred dollars and you
say no I don't, we're a little concerned that I might be
telling the truth because I wouldn't סתם stam make that up out
of nowhere. You might deny it even though it's true, and that
doesn't mean you're a bad guy, it might just mean you're buying
time. But I probably wouldn't demand it if there was nothing behind
it. So that enough makes us see that there's enough validity to
have you make a שבועה. shvuah.
Yes. So what happens to the creditor, is he allowed to bring
the guy to court again later on, say you do owe me
that money, and how does that work out?
What do you mean?
In other words, the person who borrowed the money, he's denying it
because he wants to gain time. Right. So he could also just
forget the whole thing, decide well I'm not paying him now.
Well that's why exactly we make him make a שבועה. shvuah. Oh
okay. I say you owe me the hundred dollars, you say you
don't, we say well we think
Dov is telling the truth because Dov wouldn't make that up out
of nowhere, but David might deny it just to buy himself time.
So how are we going to get to the bottom of this?
So rather than just saying David gets to walk off, which is
what the משנה Mishna says, כופר הכל kofer ha'kol you get to
walk off, we're going to say before we let David walk off
we're going to make him make a שבועה. shvuah. And that's exactly
what רב נחמן Rav Nachman is saying.
And I might hesitate to make a שבועה. shvuah.
And you might say no I'm not going to make a שבועה,
shvuah, I'll pay you instead.
Or which would be a good scheme on your part.
Right. But the thing is as we're about to see, the principle,
is the principle מתוך שאינו יכול להישבע משלם, mitoch she'eino yachol l'hishava
meshalem, if you're not able to make a שבועה shvuah you have
to pay, is that really
true in by what do you call it, by this rabbinic שבועה?
shvuah? That's true by a דאורייתא d'oraisa שבועה. shvuah. So one possibility
is that you'll make a שבועה shvuah and then our misgivings will
be set aside. You made a שבועה shvuah now we believe more
that you're telling the truth. Right. The other question is that you
say I don't want to make a שבועה. shvuah. So what's the
consequence of refusing to make a שבועה shvuah by שבועת היסת? shvuat
hesset? Presumably it would be,
on the one hand it's not a weighty שבועה דאורייתא shvuah d'oraisa
so maybe you don't have to pay because we don't really like
in a heavy way think you owe the money, in a concerned
way we're maybe you owe the money, so is that enough to
say you have to pay?
So it's not clear.
Well, the שבועה shvuah is then that everybody goes ahead and says
oh, so David said he didn't owe the money, but then he
wouldn't go ahead and make the שבועה, shvuah, maybe there's like some
social pressure and that. It's not exactly
clear what is the consequence of you not making the שבועה? shvuah?
Let's hold off, we're going to have that somewhat of that discussion
coming up.
Doesn't it have then that metaphysical effect you were talking about yesterday
with that heavy?
Well
that's a good question too because whatever the nature of the obligation
is, if it's a שבועת שקר, shvuat sheker, then it still is
a שבועת שקר, shvuat sheker, right? It doesn't almost matter where the
obligation is coming from, you're still taking an oath about something that
is false, okay? So you might have... those metaphysical implications, you know,
that we talked about yesterday. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, רב חביבי מתני אסיפא. Rav Chavivi matni a'seifa.
Now that's רב נחמן's Rav Nachman saying this about the case where
the guy's כופר הכל. kofer kol. But רב חביבי Rav Chavivi teaches
this on the end of the משנה. Mishnah. מנה לי בידך, Maneh
li b'yadecha. you owe me $100. אמר לו הן, amar lo hen,
yes. למחר אמר לו תנהו לי, lemachar amar lo teneihu li, give
it to me. נתתי לך, nasatti lach, I paid you up. פטור,
you're exempt. So there he also is exempt by saying I totally
paid you up, but there at least we know that initially he
owed the money. Okay, and in that case, אמר רב נחמן משבינן
אותו שבועת היסת. amar Rav Nachman mashbinan oto shevuat hesset. That's the
case where the guy has to take a שבועה. shevua. Okay, and
now we understand that's a little different. That's a case where you
start by knowing that there actually was a debt. Okay, and that's
a little bit more understandable that we can impose a שבועה shevua
in that case. So מן דמתני ארישא כל שכן אסיפא. man de-matni
a'reisha kol sheken a'seifa. If you can impose a שבועה shevua in
the first case where there's absolutely no basis except this guy's claim,
then of course you would apply it in the second case. Pretty
much a שבועת היסת shevuat hesset you could almost always apply, right?
Imagine any single court case. I'm trying to get money from David,
whatever the case is, if it's about torts, if it's about a
contract, if it's about a million things, it's a he-said he-said, okay,
and therefore if David's denying, and if I don't have evidence and
David can walk off, I can always say wait, before you walk
off, make him make a שבועת היסת, shevuat hesset, right? It becomes
almost this generic שבועה. shevua. All right, but according to the first
version, I almost don't even need to substantiate anything. I just need
to make the claim, okay? But מן דמתני אסיפא, man de-matni a'seifa,
but if you say it only applies in the second case, top
of מ"א ע"א, mem-aleph amud-aleph,
where there actually was evidence that there was a debt, and now
the question was, was the debt paid off? So הכא הוא דאיכא
דררא דממונא. hacha hu de-ika drora de-mamona. You would make a שבועה
shevua when there is a דררא דממונא. drora de-mamona. There's a whole
major debate in ראשונים Rishonim what exactly that means, but what but
it's basically understood to mean that there is basically some type of
like, I don't know, שייכות ממון, shaychus mamon, meaning that there's clearly
some
substantiating basis, you know, it's clear that there was some existing monetary
obligation that existed, you know, that was present. You already know that
I have, maybe the way to say this is sort of like
you already know that I have some legitimate claim on David's money.
Now maybe that claim was addressed or maybe not, but there's I
already it's not like I'm coming out of the blue. Okay, and
therefore it has to be countered. אבל התם דליכא דררא דממונא, aval
hatam de-leika drora de-mamona, in
the other case where there's no established connection to the money, לא,
lo, you would not you would not take the שבועת היסת. shevuat
hesset.
Now what is the הלכה? halacha? Michael always wants to know what
the הלכה halacha is because obviously if you don't even need a
דררא דממונא, drora de-mamona, right, you can use this left and right,
you can use this any single time. Okay, so take a look
at תוספות. Tosafot. מן דמתני אסיפא, man de-matni a'seifa, תוספות Tosafot says:
אמר רבינו תם השתא דלא איתמר הלכתא
כחד מהני לישני, amar Rabbeinu Tam hashta de-lo itmar hilcheta ke-chad mei-hanei
lishni,
we haven't ruled one way or the other, so היכא דליכא דררא
דממונא, heicha de-leika drora de-mamona, if there's not already some established basis
that the guy has some claim, לא משבינן ליה מספק דהמוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. lo mashbinan lei mi-safek de-hamotzi mei-chavero alav ha-reiya.
So it's almost like normally we say I can't take money out
of you without proof, but I also can't extract a שבועה shevua
from you without proof. Okay, if there's a debate whether I'm entitled
to impose a שבועה, shevua, do we impose a שבועה shevua when
there's no דררא דממונא, drora de-mamona, when it's just a claim out
of the blue? So תוספות Tosafot says if there's a debate about
whether you can do it, you can't do it. The same way
if there's a debate about money I can't make you pay if
there's a debate, if there's a debate if I can demand a
שבועה shevua from you, I can't make you take a שבועה. shevua.
ואף על פי כן, ve-af al pi chen, so that's what רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam said. Okay, and nevertheless, לא היה מוחה בדיינים המשביעים.
lo haya mocheh ba-dayanim ha-mashbi'im.
Apparently judges liked to use it, right? You can imagine why judges
liked to use it. They figure it'll get people to tell the
truth more,
it'll
solve the conscience, they'll be able to feel that if we're פסקינן
paskening to let the guy free and he said what he said
with a שבועה, shevua, we feel better about it, okay? And then
he says וקצת נראה להשביע. ve-ktzat nireh le-hashbi'a. תוספות Tosafot says
it actually makes sense we should do it even in cases where
there's no דררא דממונא. drora de-mamona. דאיכא דאמרי טפי ללשון ראשון. de-ika
de-amri tfei le-lishon rishon.
It's a good important הלכה halachic principle. The גמרא Gemara says the
first version was רב נחמן Rav Nachman said it on the first
part of the משנה, Mishnah, even when there was no basis, just
סתם stam a claim. איכא דאמרי ika de-amri he only said it
when the guy admitted initially that he owed the money. So תוספות
Tosafot says an איכא דאמרי ika de-amri always is considered to be
less weighty than the first version. The first version of the events
is always considered more to be the default interpretation. And since the
first version was that רב נחמן Rav Nachman said it even without
a דררא דממונא, drora de-mamona, we should rule that way. Okay, so
don't we do לישנא בתרא lishon batra usually though?
We have that concept as well? Yeah, that's a good question. Okay,
that's why תוספות's Tosafot next line is כמו שאומר ריב"א. kmo she-omer
Riva. Okay, so there is a question about is לישנא בתרא lishon
batra the
same as an איכא דאמרי ika de-amri or not? Anyway, מיהו mihu
it's a
very good question which I'm not going to unpack now.
מיהו אמר רבינו תם דאזלינן בתר המקל mihu amar Rabbeinu Tam d'azlinan
batar ha-mekil that with an איכא דאמרי ika de-amri we go by
the more lenient one. And now what's the more lenient one? The
more lenient one is don't impose a שבועה. shevua. Okay, now anyway,
I want to keep on reading this one more so you get
a sense of what a דררא דממונא drora de-mamona is. And he
says like this: וכן משמע בפרק קמא דבבא מציעא גבי ההוא רעיא
דמייתי התם מילתא דרב נחמן ארישא דמתניתין. ve-chen mashma be-perek kama de-Bava
Metzia gabbei ha-hu raya de-maiti hatam milta de-Rav Nachman a-reisha de-matnitin. Okay,
that there was a case about a shepherd that we brought there
the words of רב נחמן Rav Nachman on the first part of
our משנה. Mishnah. day they used to give him a certain amount
of sheep and then there was a claim about blah blah blah.
Anyway, and they made him make a שבועת היסת. shvuas heses. רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam דוחה, doche, דאיכא למימר דהתם רישא דמילתא נקט בזבינו.
d'ika l'meimar d'hasam reisha d'milsa nakat b'zveinu. Okay, wait, hold on, I'm
skipping a little. דהתם נמי איכא דרורא דממונא, d'hasam nami ika drora
d'mamona, about, I skipped like three lines, מאחר שהיו רגילים למסור לו
בכל יום. me-achar she-hayu regilim limsor lo bechol yom. Okay, so anyway,
there's a question about what constitutes, I probably shouldn't have gone into
that without a text, but anyway, there's a question what constitutes דרורא
דממונא. drora d'mamona. So if I know that every day I gave
you, you know, this was a guy that we would every single
day have watch our sheep. And the story was every day they
had watch our sheep and they didn't trust this guy, okay, and
they always made sure that there were witnesses. And one day when
they gave him the sheep to watch, the shepherd, and one day
they gave him the sheep without witnesses, at least that's what they
claim, and then they said, and then he said, "Hey, you didn't
give me sheep today." So they made him take a שבועת היסת,
shvuas heses, okay? So the question is, is that a שבועת היסת
shvuas heses with a, without a דרורא דממונא drora d'mamona or with
a דרורא דממונא? drora d'mamona? Today, on Monday, there's no evidence that
we gave that we gave him the sheep. But based on the
pattern we've established for the last year, we give him the sheep
on a daily basis. So, so you know, so is that a
דרורא דממונא drora d'mamona or not? תוספות Tosafot says רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam says that can work with his approach that you need a
דרורא דממונא, drora d'mamona, because even though there's no evidence today, all
of the evidence around it substantiates the likelihood that they did give
him the sheep. So that's an interesting question of what constitutes דרורא
דממונא. drora d'mamona. Anyway, דרורא דממונא, drora d'mamona, okay, so the word
ממונא mamona means money. דרורא, drora, there's a debate what it means,
but the ראשונים Rishonim sort of say like a connection to the
money. You establish that you have some, it's not just a claim
is out of the blue, you're, you know, there's some reason that,
you know, you're establishing you have some connection to the money that
you're claiming. Any different word דרורא? drora? דרורא, drora, they say it's
like שייכות, shaychus, I don't know. Okay, think of ציפור דרור. tzippor
dror. Yeah, I don't know, I don't know what to say. Okay,
so anyway, so we have an interesting question about whether we say,
how do we פסקן? pasken? Do we פסקן, pasken, you know, you
need a דרורא דממונא drora d'mamona or not? You know, can you
impose this שבועת היסת? shvuas heses? Now we want to understand what's
the weight of this שבועת היסת? shvuas heses? And it was right
to ask, you know, the גמרא Gemara sort of speaks about all
of the ways we scare somebody before taking a שבועה shvuah because
of the power of the שבועת שקר. shvuas sheker. But presumably that's
not a question of the obligation, that's just taking a שבועת שקר
shvuas sheker even if you take it out of בית דין, beis
din, even if you just סתם stam take it on your own.
It's just when it's in בית דין beis din we can put
the fear of God into you. Okay, so what is the difference
between these? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי איכא בין
שבועה דאורייתא לשבועה דרבנן? mai ika bein shvua d'Oraisa l'shvua d'Rabbanan? What
is, what's the difference between these two שבועות? shvuos? Now I want
to again clarify that this שבועה דרבנן shvua d'Rabbanan does not mean
the שבועה דרבנן shvua d'Rabbanan we're going to see later of the
small number of cases where you can take a שבועה shvua and
actually extract money from the other side. This שבועה דרבנן shvua d'Rabbanan
specifically means שבועת היסת. shvuas heses. What's the difference? נקיטת חפץ nekisas
cheifetz and all? Well, okay, so Michael suggests something which I'll get
back to. It's not what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי איכא בין
שבועה דאורייתא לשבועה דרבנן? איכא בינייהו מהפך שבועה. mai ika bein shvua
d'Oraisa l'shvua d'Rabbanan? Ika beiniyahu mehapaich shvua. Reversing the שבועה. דאורייתא shvua
doraisa, לא מהפכינן, lo mehaphinan שבועה shvuah. דרבנן d'Rabbanan, מהפכינן. mehaphinan. Okay,
so let's say I have to take a שבועה, shvuah, a שבועה
shvuah of מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, and I say, "I don't want
to take it. David, you ask, you say I owe you a
hundred dollars, I say only owe you fifty. I don't want to
swear on the other fifty. If you swear, I'll pay you." Okay?
So that's מהפכינן. mehaphinan Can I have the option of reversing it
to the other side? I'll tell you what, you swear and then
I'll pay. So here it's saying, for דאורייתא d'Oraisa you can't. If
I refuse to swear, then I can't make you swear, I just
have to pay, period, okay? If I'm not going to take the
שבועה, shvuah, I don't have a right to reverse it to the
other side. Take the שבועה shvuah or pay. But בדרבנן מהפכינן. b'd'Rabbanan
mehaphinan. By the דרבנן, d'Rabbanan I can say, "I don't want to,
I want you to do it." Okay? So ולמר בר רב אשי
דאמר בדאורייתא נמי מהפכינן. u'l'Mar bar Rav Ashi d'amar b'd'Oraisa nami mehaphinan.
Wait a minute, מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi says
even by a דאורייתא d'Oraisa you're entitled to swap, you know, reverse
it to the other side. But the other side can't object? No,
no, I'd really rather you take it. Well, no, he can't. Meaning,
the fact that if I don't take the שבועה shvuah it has
to translate into paying, then I could say, you know, "I refuse
to take the שבועה shvuah and I will pay you if you'll
swear." And if you say, "I won't swear either," then presumably we
would both walk away. That's the חידוש chiddush of מהפך שבועה. mehapaich
shvua. Okay? So they could be both like both uncertain and with
good intentions. Yeah, but then it's a, but but you would not,
you don't obligate a שבועה, shvuah, that's a question, can you obligate
a שבועה shvuah by a טענת ספק? ta'anas safek? All our cases
is that you're saying, "I definitely owe you the money," if you're
saying, "I think you might owe me the money," and I say,
"I don't know," like anyway, if you only say you think, okay,
then it's interesting. Let's say you think but there's an עד אחד
eid echad that say I definitely does, or you say you think
and it's a שומרים shomrim case. So questions about a שבועה shvua
by a טענת שמא ta'anas shema we haven't dealt with. Okay, so
anyway let's read this through and then we'll sort of pull it
all together. Okay? מהפכינן means you actually, you have the absolute right.
You have the right to switch it to the other side. And
the other and the other side has to then agree. And the
other side either takes the שבועה shvua or doesn't get paid, presumably.
And לא מהפכינן means that no, if you're not prepared to take
it, you pay. Okay? So אם דאורייתא im d'Oraisa even though you
have to swear, according to this opinion it says you can switch
it around. And you can turn the tables on me, then I
have no recourse if I don't want to, if I'm demanding money
of you. Right. Okay. למאן דרב אשי דאמר בדאורייתא נמי מפכינן, L'man
d'Rav Ashi d'amar b'd'Oraisa nami mapchinin, לבר מדרב מר בר רב אשי
l'var m'd'Rav Mar bar Rav Ashi that you also reverse it by
a דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, נמי מפכינן שבועה, nami mapchinin shevuah, מאי איכא בין
דאורייתא לדרבנן? mai ika bein d'Oraisa l'd'Rabbanan? So if you can reverse
both of them, what's the difference? איכא בינייהו מיחת לנכסי, Ika beinihu
mechas l'nechsei, whether if the guy refuses to take the שבועה shevuah
and now we're getting to the consequence of refusing to take the
שבועה, shevuah, okay, if the guy refuses to take the שבועה, shevuah,
will we basically go and seize his property as a result? So
now that's the consequence. You told me I'm חייב chayav a שבועה
shevuah of א מודה במקצת a modeh b'miktzas and I say I
refuse to swear. So, will בית דין beis din now go and
seize my Chevy to pay for the remaining 50 bucks or whatever
it is? Okay? So, will they seize my property to pay for
the for the amount that the שבועה shevuah was supposed to be
about that I was refusing to swear about? You used to drive
a Ferrari. I know. Well, it's only 50 bucks now. Okay. So,
okay, so נכסי. nechsei. So now the גמרא Gemara says בדאורייתא נחתינן
לנכסי, בדרבנן לא נחתינן לנכסי. B'd'Oraisa nechtinan l'nechsei, b'd'Rabbanan lo nechtinan l'nechsei.
Now this though makes it sound that going back to the question
raised before, that if I refuse to take a שבועת היסת, shevuas
heises, I do owe you the money, okay, but the court won't
act on it. So that's an interesting middle position we didn't imagine.
Okay, you say Dave says I owe you $100. I say to
Dave, you owe me $100, and Dave says, no, I don't owe
you a penny. Here, take a שבועת היסת. shevuas heises. Dave says
I refuse to swear. So what's the consequence of refusing to swear?
So according to this, it's like the court says, Dave, you have
to pay Dov $100. We're not going to go ahead and seize
it. If you do the right thing, you'll pay it to him.
We're not going to actually send the sheriff after you. So that's
like an interesting middle position, that the consequence of not doing a
שבועת היסת shevuas heises is you owe the money, but the court
won't back that up by sending in the sheriff after you. Okay.
ולרב יוסף. U'l'Rav Yosef. So the גמרא Gemara says ולרב יוסף דאמר
בדרבנן נמי נחתינן לנכסי. U'l'Rav Yosef d'amar b'd'Rabbanan nami nechtinan l'nechsei. One
minute, but according to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef
says that by cases of like a rabbinic type of a obligation,
we also would go to the guys, seize the guy's property. דתנן,
Detnan, how do we know רב יוסף Rav Yosef says this? Because
he says, מציאת חרש שוטה וקטן יש בהם גזל מפני דרכי שלום.
Metzias cheresh shoteh v'katan yesh bahem gezel mipnei darchei shalom. That if
a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh v'katan, somebody who's not able to
take legal possession of an object, finds an object on the street,
okay, then it's considered theirs, but it's only considered theirs because of
like דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, the nice, you know, the in order
to make for a well-running society. They're not legally the owners. ורב
יוסף אמר גזל גמור. V'Rav Yosef amar gezel gamur. No, actually, it
we are legally it's rabbinic, but we're going to legally consider them
the owners. Meaning so if you went to a court and you
said, who is the owners of this object? According to the first
opinion, it would be, well, nobody owns the object, but we let
we're letting, you know, that person hold keep it because, you know,
for for public policy, for whatever it is, for the well-running of
society. Whereas רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, no, we rabbinically have decreed
that that person owns it. Okay, it's still rabbinic, but it's considered
his. So the גמרא Gemara says למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai nafka mina?
ואמר רב חסדא דגזל גמור מדבריהם. V'amar Rav Chisda d'gezel gamur midivreihem.
It's rabbinically his. So they all agree, except one says the rabbis
instituted that he owns it, and the other said the rabbis instituted
that we shouldn't take it away from him, that like we should
like, you know, treat it as if it's his, but not that
legally he owns it. Okay, and the so that's so that seems
like only a hair's breadth difference. So the גמרא Gemara says למאי
נפקא מינה, L'mai nafka mina, what difference does that make? להוציאו בדיינין.
L'hotzi'o b'dayanin. Because according to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, since you're calling
it really his, that means let's say somebody went ahead and and
did snatch it out of the hand of this of this חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan that found it. So according to the
first opinion, they would say, okay, that was just we were telling
people you shouldn't, okay? We never are legally saying that it was
his. So the guy ripped it didn't listen to us, he violated
that rule that you, you know, you shouldn't take it away from
them, but the קטן katan has no legal recourse, okay? Whereas רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says, no, legally we said it was the קטן's
katan and he has legal recourse and he can get it back
from that guy. Fine. So the גמרא Gemara now is globalizing, and
תוספות Tosafos doesn't understand why it's globalizing because it really seems that
that's just a local debate by how we treat the מציאה, metziah,
the the finding of an object when a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan finds a lost object, right? That they debate, is it
only a תיקון עולם tikun olam or is it דרבנן derabbanan, ownership?
It doesn't so but it would seem like that everybody would agree
that in a case where really the rabbis do award something to
somebody, that we would back that up with, you know, and really
להוציאו בדיינין, l'hotzi'o b'dayanin, say that the courts would protect that right.
So the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like they're having some global
debate. When something emerges from a rabbinic ruling or an obligation, according
to the חכמים, chachamim, we don't back it up with the police,
and according to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, we do back it up
with the police. Okay, but תוספות Tosafos says, why are we saying
that? Everybody would agree we back it up with the police. The
only point is that the rabbis are saying the קטן katan is
not is not recognized as the legal owner, right? It's just that
they didn't even award it to the קטן katan in that case.
But okay, bracket that. So the גמרא Gemara is basically basically reading
this debate as being a global one. The גמרא Gemara says is,
if according to רב יוסי Reb Yosi you back up rabbinic things
with the police and they will actually come and take some money
away, right, from the person who took it from the קטן, katan,
so then in this case of שבועת היסת, Shvuas Heses, if you
refuse to make the שבועה, shvua, even if it's only a rabbinically
imposed שבועה, shvua, we should back up that we should back up
the שבועה shvua and we should go ahead and, you know, and
and send the police after you and make you pay the money.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says, so what would be the
difference? איכא בינייהו, Ika beinayhu, now I just want to pause again
for a moment before we say that, because there's still a big
difference, right? It's one thing if we say the rabbis say the
קטן katan owns this object and then somebody stole it from the
קטן, katan, we're going to go and take it away from that
person and give it back to the קטן, katan, because we direct
the nature of what the rabbis said was, we recognize the קטן
katan as the legal owner. But when what the rabbis said was,
when I come to David and says he owes me a hundred
dollars and David says he doesn't, that David has to take a
שבועה, shvua, we never said anything about this money. All we said
was David had to take a שבועה. shvua. So meaning the big
question about how do we know that if he refuses the שבועה
shvua he owe rabbinically he owes me the money and therefore we're
going to send the police after him, fine, if rabbinically he owes
me the money we will send the police after him, but how
did we how do we know to say that? All we said
was that he has to make a שבועה. shvua. How do we
know to say that if he doesn't make a שבועה shvua then
rabbinically he owes me the money? Right, so that again the גמרא
Gemara is taken for granted. So the simple reading of the גמרא
Gemara is is that if you take a שבועת היסת, Shvuas Heses,
if you refuse to take the שבועת היסת, Shvuas Heses, the same
way if you refuse to take a שבועה דאורייתא, shvua d'Oraita, you
actually owe the money to the person and we will send the
police after you. Okay, so it's pretty pretty weighty, there's not a
big difference anymore, right, we're going to go ahead and send the
police after you. So and you owe the money. So what is
the difference then? איכא בינייהו שכנגדו חשוד על השבועה. Ika beinayhu sheknegedo
chashud al hashvua. The difference would be let's say David is not
able to take a שבועה shvua because he was a known to
be a gambler or he's known to be a person that takes
false oaths. So now what happens when you try to impose a
שבועה shvua on someone who can't impose it? So בדאורייתא שכנגדו חשוד
על השבועה, bidoraisa sheknegedo chashud al hashvua, in a דאורייתא doraisa obligation
if David has to take a שבועה מודה במקצת shvua modeh bemiktzas
and he's not able to because he is let's say known to
lie under oath, so in that case אפכינן ליה שבועה ושדינא אאידך.
afchinan lei shvua veshadina aidach. We reverse it and we put it
on the other side. So before the question was does David have
the right to reverse it? If David just doesn't want to, can
he say Dov, you take the שבועה shvua and you take it.
Here the question is not does he have the right to if
he's if it's not possible for him to take the שבועה, shvua,
what do what do we do then? So by a דאורייתא doraisa
we say the other side takes שבועה shvua and collects. בדרבנן תקנתא
היא, biderrabbanan takanta hi, but בדרבנן biderrabbanan we would not go that
far to say that if David can't do it that then I'm
going then then then I'm going to have the right to do
it and take the money away from him. ותקנתא לתקנתא לא עבדינן,
vetakanta letakanta lo avdinan, and we don't make a תקנתא takanta on
top of a תקנתא. takanta. Okay, so therefore what we basically do
is we say if David can't make it then he gets off
scot-free. It's a little ironic because David is a known to swear
falsely, he gets off the hook by a שבועת היסת. Shvuas Heses.
Okay, so basically, so what have we sort of said? This is
really an excellent גמרא Gemara because besides identifying the difference between דאורייתא
doraisa and דרבנן, derabbanan right, it basically tells you what happens by
a שבועה, shvua, different things about a שבועה. shvua. So here's the
case, okay, so you have to take a שבועה. shvua. Now here
are some scenarios. I don't want to, okay. That's one scenario. Okay
now that could break up in two. One is like you take
it, okay, and you take it and then you'll win, right, and
whatever and I'll pay, you take it and I'll pay. Okay that's
a case of מיפך שבועה. meiphach shvua. Then you reverse it to
the other side. Okay another scenario is I just don't want to
and period, not you take it and I'll pay. I don't want
to, I refuse, right. So what's the consequence of I refuse? Okay
so consequence so okay, and the other is I can't take it,
right, which is a case about חשוד. chashud. Okay so what's the
consequence there? All right, so I guess so how are we going
to do this? Guess we'll do this like this. Okay so this
is right דאורייתא doraisa and this is and this is whatever שבועת
היסת. Shvuas Heses. Okay so מיפך שבועה, meiphach shvua, can you do
this? I didn't give myself a lot of room there anyway. All
right, so if the guy says I don't want to, you take
it and I'll pay, okay, so one says by שבועת היסת Shvuas
Heses what was First answer. בדאורייתא Be'De'Oraita מיפך מיפך שבועה, Mei-Pach Mei-Pach
Shvuos, דאורייתא De'Oraita לא מפכינן. Lo Mafchinin. So according to one it's
no, it's like, no, no. The נתבע Nitva just pays, you know,
תובע Toveia doesn't have to have to and the נתבע Nitva pays,
right? That that's לא מפכינן. Lo Mafchinin. And this is just תובע
Toveia has to. Okay, so that's that's what that was the first
answer. The guy says, "I don't want to, you take it and
I'll pay." According to one answer that's in this case, you don't
have to, you don't have to take the שבועה. Shvuos. You just,
you know, the other side just pays without the שבועה. Shvuos. This
is no, you're allowed to put it on the other side and
they do have to take the שבועה. Shvuos. Okay, the other, I'm
not sure if this is, whatever. The other case is he's just
refusing to take it altogether. Okay, so in this case pay and
we send the police, that's נחתינן לנכסיה. Nachtinan Le'Nichsei. Send the police.
Okay, in this case it's pay, but we don't send the police.
That's what we said we do send the police. Okay, I mean
the גמרא Gemara then rejected that. The גמרא Gemara says maybe we
do even in that case as well. I'm just saying the גמרא
Gemara was suggesting these points of difference. Okay, and then in this
case I can't take it. Okay, so in this case pay. I
just need to do this. I'm a little bit I guess I
didn't give myself enough room here. Hold on. Okay, anyway, fine. This
is דאורייתא De'Oraita and this is היסת. Heset. Okay, so in this
case, okay, let's start with this. The guy refuses, right? So in
both of these cases it's basically pay if the guy refuses, but
the question is do we send the police? Police check and here
we'll do it like this way, police question mark, right? That was
the question. Okay, but in both cases he doesn't want to pay.
In this case, you take it and I'll pay. Okay, so the
question was here, everybody agrees that basically תובע Toveia takes שבועה Shvuos
and collects. And here the question is does the תובע Toveia even
have to take the שבועה? Shvuos? Okay, maybe you're not allowed, maybe
the תובע Toveia can say, "I refuse to take the שבועה, Shvuos,
pay me anyway. You're not you're not taking it." Okay, so תובע
Toveia we don't know if the תובע Toveia has to. Okay. So
can you reverse the biblical oath? That's the question. The גמרא Gemara
had a debate. Maybe it doesn't have to. Okay. And then this
case I can't take it. Here basically the answer is pay and
here the answer is don't pay. Okay. So if you want to
give somebody a chance
who you know is suspect, you're taking a double jeopardy because he
won't be able to impose an oath on. Correct. That is correct.
That would be really stupid of you. Collects and שבועה Shvuos is
a question mark. Okay. All right, so let's take a look. I
hope that's clarified it somewhat.
Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ורבנן, Ve'Rabbanan, says
the גמרא, Gemara, דפליגי עליה דרבי יוסי, De'Pligi Alei De'Rabbi Yosi, דאמרי
בדרבנן לא נחתינן לנכסיה. De'Amri Be'De'Rabbanan Lo Nachtinan Le'Nichsei.
So now the גמרא Gemara is choosing to read this as a
big global debate that the Rabbis would say we never back up
our things with sending in the police. So according to them that
you don't send in the police, right? So basically he refuses to
take it and we say he pay but we're not going to
send in the police. If that's true, מאי עבדינן ליה? Mai Avdinan
Lei? How do we get him to pay if he refuses to
take the שבועה? Shvuos? משמתינן ליה, Meshamtinan Lei, we put him in
חרם. Cherem. Okay, so אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar Lei Ravina
Le'Rav Ashi, הני נקיטי בכובסיה דנשפיה לגלימיה הוא. Hani Naktei Be'Kuvsei De'Nishpakei
Le'Glimei Hu. So that is רש״י Rashi says that this is a
little bit of a crude expression. You're holding him by his blank,
okay, I'll let you figure it out, by the thing that is
suspending from his body is what רש״י Rashi says the word כובסיה
Kuvsei means, okay, in order for and getting him to give you
his cloak. Okay, so basically very nice that you didn't send in
the police, by putting him in חרם Cherem you're using pretty darn,
you know, persuasive you're basically forcing him through social pressure, you know,
at the end of the day this is just the same thing.
אלא מאי עבדינן ליה? Ela Mai Avdinan Lei? Fine, what do we
do to him? אמר ליה משמתינן ליה עד דמטי זמן נגדיה. Amar
Lei Meshamtinan Lei Ad De'Mati Zman Negdei. We fine, we don't put
him in חרם Cherem indefinitely. We put him in חרם Cherem until
the point where he deserves lashes because the הלכה Halachah is somebody
who's in חרם Cherem and doesn't do something to rectify it for
30 days, we rabbinically give the person lashes. So we keep him
in חרם Cherem for 30 days. ונגדינן unagdinan ליה, lei, and then
we give him lashes, and then ושבקינן veshavkinan ליה, lei, and then
we release him from his חרם. cherem. So it's like a one-month
throw him in jail for contempt of court, but then he gets
freed eventually. And if he's willing to undergo that, then we'll do
that and he won't have to pay. Okay? So there—so there is
the big difference, therefore, I think this, right, the whole point here,
right, is, I think the case of חשוד chashud is an unusual
one. But the real question this is asking is, how weighty is
this שבועה shvua obligation in the sense of will it ever translate
into paying money if it's only this דרבנן derabbanan שבועה? shvua? Okay.
And the basic point is, yes, we do want you to pay
money even for this דרבנן שבועה, shvua, but we're just not going
to force it to the same degree. Okay? We might not send
the police after you; we'll still try to pressure you to pay.
That's what's being debated. Okay. Maybe we won't make you pay unless
the other guy will take the שבועה, shvua, whereas in a דאורייתא
de'oraita maybe even if the other guy doesn't take a שבועה shvua
we'll make you pay. Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Now by the way, you know, there's Michael was here as
he said, maybe the גמרא Gemara should be talking about the legal
ramifications of the differences. But the question also is, is there a
difference in terms of how we—the ritual of taking the שבועה? shvua?
Because when we started this פרק perek we all spoke about, you
know, using God's name and taking—holding onto an object, and, like a
ספר תורה. sefer Torah. So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he
says, so he quotes רש"י Rashi as saying, מאי איכא בין שבועה
דאורייתא לשבועה דרבנן? mai ika bein shvua de'oraita lishvua derabbanan? פרק הכותב
perek Hakotev גבי הא דאמר רב נחמן gabei ha de'amar Rav Nachman
הפיקח שומע hapike'ach shome'a מייתי ליה לידי שבועה דאורייתא. maiti lei lidei
shvua de'oraita. פירש בקונטרס peirash be'kuntres דנפקא מינה denafka mina דבדאורייתא debid'oraita
בעי למינקט חפצא בידיה ba'ei leminat chafza beyadei ובדרבנן uviderabbanan לא בעי.
lo ba'ei. Okay. He says that רש"י Rashi says the difference is
that in the ritual is that by a דאורייתא de'oraita you hold
onto a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, but by a שבועת היסת shvuat
hesseit you're not going to have to hold onto a ספר תורה
sefer Torah or תפילין. tefillin. רמב"ם Rambam says the same thing. רמב"ם
Rambam says that by a שבועת היסת shvuat hesseit the officer of
the court who's imposing the oath holds onto the ספר תורה, sefer
Torah, but the person taking the oath does not hold onto the
ספר תורה. sefer Torah. תוספות Tosafot disagrees. תוספות Tosafot says, no, that's—the
ritual is the exact same. Okay, so that—there's an interesting question there,
which is: is there a difference in the ritual of the שבועת
היסת, shvuat hesseit, that a שבועת היסת shvuat hesseit maybe we don't
insist you hold onto a ספר תורה? sefer Torah? Alright, so that's
that issue. Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now
let's continue. אמר רב פפא: amar Rav Papa: האי מאן דאפיק שטרא
אחבריה hai man de'afik shtara achavreih ואמר ליה: שטרא פרוע הוא. ve'amar
lei shtara parua hu. Somebody who basically—so now, rather than me just
saying David owes me a hundred dollars and he denies it, I
actually extract an IOU that said that, you know, a written document
with witnesses that said that David owed me a hundred dollars. And
David says, yeah, I paid it off already; you know, you were
supposed to give it back to me. Okay. ואמר ליה ve'amar lei:
שטרא פרוע הוא. shtara parua hu. אמינא ליה: aminan lei: לאו כל
כמינך, lav kol kminach, זיל שלים. zil shalim. Okay. We say, yeah,
we don't believe you, obviously. You're not believed to say you've paid
it up if the guy's holding onto a שטר. shtar. ואי אמר
לישתבע לי, ve'ei amar lishtava li, but if David says, fine, I'll
pay him because he's got a שטר, shtar, you know, I totally
lose in this case, right? That's—that's like—this is the exact reverse of
a כופר בכל. kofer hakol. Normal כופר בכל kofer hakol is I
come with no evidence and David says I don't owe, and David
should be able to walk away, but maybe we make him make
a שבועת היסת. shvuat hesseit. Here, I come with the big guns;
I've got a שטר, shtar, and David says I don't owe you,
and David is completely not believed. Okay, but here's what's going to
happen. If David then says, ואי אמר לישתבע לי, ve'ei amar lishtava
li, David says: I want Dov to take a שבועה shvua to
me before I pay him! Okay, fine. It's the reverse case. Here,
the other case, I was going to lose—I was going to walk
away, and you said make a שבועה shvua before I walk away.
Here, Dov is going to get his hundred dollars; let him take
a שבועה shvua before he takes his hundred dollars. Okay. אמינא ליה:
aminan lei: אשתבע ליה. ishtava lei. We say to him: Yeah, Dov,
take a שבועה shvua to him. Okay. So this sounds like a
different version of a שבועת היסת. shvuat hesseit. But what's funny here
is that like I'm like backed up with a whole שטר. shtar.
Okay. And nevertheless, אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי:
amar lei Rav Acha breih de'Rav Yosef le'Rav Ashi: ומה בין זה
לפוגם את שטרו? u'mah bein zeh le'pogem et shtaro? How is that
different? One of the rabbinic cases of a שבועה shvua is a
case where actually David—where actually I admit that the שטר shtar has
been partially paid. David says—I say, David, pay up this hundred dollars
you owe me, and David says I paid it all back, and
I say you didn't pay it all back; you paid back twenty
bucks, you still owe me the other eighty. So I've already admitted
he paid me twenty. So once I've already admitted that the שטר
shtar is not exactly—like it's not pristine, I've פוגם pogem it, I've
like injured the שטר, shtar, I've conceded that part of it is
paid. That case the rabbis insist that I make a שבועה. shvua.
So now we're saying, but you're telling me even when the שטר
shtar has not been, you know, somehow impinged upon, right, that you
can go ahead and be obligated to make a שבועה? shvua? So
every time a guy takes out a שטר shtar you have to
make a שבועה? shvua? And why do we make a specific תקנה
takkanah that in the case of פוגם שטרו pogem shtaro where he
concedes it's partly been paid he has to make a שבועה shvua
if you're telling me he always has to make a שבועה? shvua?
ומה בין זה לפוגם את שטרו? Umah bein zeh l'pogem et shtaro?
אמר ליה התם אף על גב דלא טעין איהו טענינן ליה. Amar
lei hasam af al gav delo ta'in ihu taninan lei. In a
case where I conceded that some of it had been paid, then
even if David doesn't ask for a שבועה, shvua, we in the
court are going to say, "Dov, you can't collect the rest until
you make a שבועה." shvua. Okay. טענינן ליה אנן. Taninan lei anan.
הכא אמרינן ליה זיל שלים ליה. Hacha amrinan lei zil shlim lei.
Here we say to David, we don't suggest it, we say to
David, "David, Dov's got the שטר, shtar, go pay." ואי טעין ואמר
ישתבע לי v'i ta'in v'amar ishtava li and if David says, "Wait,
wait, wait, I want him to make a שבועה," shvua, then we
say, זיל אשתבע ליה. zil ishtava lei. Then we say, "Go ahead
and make a שבועה." shvua. Okay. So, yes, this requires David to
make the demand. Now, you know, this is also interesting, right, because
like does this show evidence about like how ready we are to
make a שבועת היסת? shvuat hesset? Here I've got a שטר shtar
backing me up, and David could demand that I, like, you know,
take a שבועת היסת shvuat hesset to show up, or take some
type of a שבועה? shvua? So part of the reason is that
תוספות Tosafot points out, I won't really go into the whole תוספות,
Tosafot, but he points out, you know, it's because we also know
the same way we know in the other case that sometimes David
says he doesn't owe me money and he does, he's only pushing
me off. We also know in cases of a שטר shtar that
it's often the case that I still have a שטר shtar even
if it's been paid up, right? That I haven't gotten around to
returning it to David, that I said, you know, that David used
to owe me the money for the cost of the סופר sofer
to write the שטר. shtar. I'm not going to give you the
שטר shtar as evidence that you paid your debt until you pay
the סופר sofer the money that we owe, his outstanding bill. You
know, there are cases where cases often, there are frequent enough cases
where the debt's been paid up and the שטר shtar hasn't been
returned. And so therefore that allows us to say that this case
as well, if a שבועה shvua is demanded, we'll make a שבועה.
shvua. It doesn't say what happens if the guy refuses to make
the שבועה, shvua, right? That's always the question. He still has a
שטר shtar behind him. You know, would he be able to collect?
I don't know, presumably yes, but it's not clear. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואי צורבא מרבנן הוא, v'i tzurva
meRabanan hu, הכא אמרינן ליה זיל אשתבע ליה, hacha amrinan lei zil
ishtava lei, ואי צורבא מרבנן הוא לא משבעינן ליה. v'i tzurva meRabanan
hu lo mashbi'inan lei. But if here, Dov, here I'm trying to
collect with my שטר, shtar, I'm a צורבא מרבנן, tzurva meRabanan, then
I don't have to take a שבועה. shvua. Now that's very interesting,
right, because it's sort of like you're impugning my integrity and my
honesty by telling me that we're not going to believe you, you
have to make a שבועה. shvua. Now normally we don't say a
צורבא מרבנן tzurva meRabanan is exempt from that, okay, because normally we're
talking about a שבועה shvua דאורייתא, whatever type of a שבועה shvua.
we're talking about, we never mentioned צורבא מרבנן tzurva meRabanan before, right?
If somebody says, "I owe a hundred dollars," and I say, "Yes
I do but I paid it up" or whatever, and we say
you have to take a שבועת היסת, shvuat hesset, so we say,
"Oh, don't take it if you're a צורבא מרבנן. tzurva meRabanan. God
forbid we would impugn your integrity." Okay. But here it's a little
different. Here I've got a שטר shtar backing me up. So if
I've got like a heavy evidence backing me up, you know, in
that case we'll waive the need of a צורבא מרבנן tzurva meRabanan
to take a שבועה. shvua You know, maybe not in other cases
where there's no good evidence or whatever. But here where I've got
this serious evidence, we don't want to demand a שבועה shvua? from
you, you're a צורבא מרבנן tzurva meRabanan and it impugns your integrity
and anyway you've got a שטר shtar backing you up, we'll give
you a pass. Okay. So just because we're giving you a pass
here doesn't mean we're giving you elsewhere. But that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. אמר ליה Amar lei but the גמרא Gemara doesn't like
this. אמר ליה רב יימר לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Yeimar l'Rav
Ashi, צורבא מרבנן משלח גלימא דאינשי? tzurva meRabanan mashlach glima d'inshi? I
don't get it. A צורבא מרבנן tzurva meRabanan has a right to
basically strip people of their cloaks? You know, like, just because he's
a צורבא מרבנן, tzurva meRabanan, why, how can you show this type
of a favoritism? It gets back to the earlier questions we had,
remember, about the עדים edim and the בעלי דין, ba'alei din, and
does one stand and one sit if it's a צורבא מרבנן? tzurva
meRabanan? Like do you show any difference in a court? People say,
"Oh, so because he's a צורבא מרבנן, tzurva meRabanan, he goes ahead,
he's able to go ahead and, you know, win the case without
having to take a שבועה? shvua. Everybody else takes a שבועה." shvua,
Like so he's just able to rob people. That's not fair. אלא,
Ella, so the גמרא Gemara says, לא מזדקקינן ליה לדיניה. lo mizdakkinan
lei l'dinei. Now this is even a worse conclusion for the case.
Okay, you're right. We can't give him a pass that he doesn't
have to take a שבועה, shvua, that introduces a real unfairness into
the system, makes it look like he's taking advantage of people. On
the other hand, we can't ask him to take a שבועה, shvua,
that impugns his integrity. So you know what we're going to do?
We'll just never hear his case, we'll always delay his case. We'll,
you know, he never gets a hearing in court. So it's crazy.
I, what does that mean? I've got a שטר shtar that David
owes me ten thousand dollars, right? I mean a lot of תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim actually were in the business of money lending, although
that was to non-Jews. Anyway, I've got a שטר shtar David owes
me ten thousand dollars and he says, "Take a שבועה," and the
court will never hear my case? Like, really? Like how does that
work? Anyway, that seems to be the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara.
It's punishing him for being a... I know. It's crazy. It's crazy.
Like so the other guy, we were rewarding the guy that was
the רשע, rasha, and we're punishing the guy that's a צורבא מרבנן.
tzurva meRabanan. Okay. מנה לי בידך. maneh li b'yadcha, Okay. So now
the guy says, "You owe me a hundred dollars." He says, "No,
I don't." He's exempt. Then he says, "Yes, I do." Then he
says, "I paid it." So if he says "I paid it," he's
actually believed. But if he says... but if he says... don't pay
me except with witnesses, and then he says he paid it, he's
not believed. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי המלווה את חבירו בעדים
צריך לפורעו בעדים. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav Assi, hamalveh et chaveiro
b'eidim tzarich l'poro b'eidim. If you lend money with witnesses, the guy
has to pay back and with witnesses. Now the question is, does
it just mean witnesses have to be present, or what it also
probably means is that it's implicit that he won't be believed to
say he paid back unless he can produce witnesses. If I had
witnesses present when I lent you the money, then implicit is any
claim you made that you've reimbursed me will not be believed unless
you can produce witnesses. אמרתי קמיה דשמואל, Amrisi kamei d'Shmuel, I said
this to Shmuel, ואמר לי, v'amar li, and Shmuel said to me,
יכול לומר לו פרעתיך בפני פלוני ופלוני והלכו להם למדינת הים. yachol
lomar lo, paraticha bifnei ploni u'ploni v'halchu lahem limdinat hayam. No, you
don't—either you don't have to pay back with witnesses at all, or
even if you do have to pay back with witnesses, you can
always claim that they were—that you had witnesses and they're not here
anymore. Which means, bottom line is, whether the act of paying back
needed witnesses, even if you lend money—according to Shmuel, even if you
lend somebody money with witnesses, they are believed to say they paid
you back without producing witnesses. Okay, that's the point of Shmuel. Now,
תנן, tnan, this really seems to be in our Mishnah. Our Mishnah
says: מנה לי בידך, אמר לו הן. Maneh li b'yadcha, amar lo
hen, You owe me a hundred dollars? Yes. And presumably yes in
front of witnesses to be a proven yes. למחר אמר לו תנהו
לי נתתי לך פטור, L'machar amar lo tneyhu li, nasati lach, patur,
you're exempt. So הכא, hacha, in this case, כיון דתבי בעדים, kivan
d'tavy b'eidim, since there were witnesses when he said you owe me
the money and he admitted to it, כמאן דאוזפי בעדים דמי, k'man
d'ozfay b'eidim dami, presumably it's exactly analogous to lending the money with
a witness. וקתני פטור, U'ktanei patur, and it says that you're believed
to say you paid back, you don't have to produce the witnesses.
It sounds like Shmuel. תיובתא דרב אסי? Tyuvta d'Rav Assi? That's a
contradiction of Rav Assi. So אמר לך רב אסי, amar lach Rav
Assi, Rav Assi would say to you: אנא כי אמרי היכא דמעיקרא
אוזפי בעדים דלא ליהימניה. Ana ki amri heicha d'me'ikara ozfay b'eidim d'lo
leideihimnei. No, no, no, I only said that you need to produce
witnesses that you paid back if initially the money was given to
you with witnesses. Which then it was clear, like I don't believe
you at the outset. Anything I'm going to do with you, David,
we are going to have it fully documented and witnesses are going
to be present, et cetera. Then I'm making it—I'm clearly telegraphing that
I do not believe you, and I don't trust you, and the
only way you can be relieved of any claim against me is
by producing witnesses. הכא הימניה, Hacha heimnei, here when I initially lent
you the money, I did it without witnesses. So in that case,
even though there were witnesses around when you admitted to the debt,
that does not mean—you still, implicit in our original transaction, was that
you would be believed—was that you would not need to produce witnesses
to be believed to say you paid. Okay. רב יוסף מתני הכי,
Rav Yosef masni hachi, so that's—this is how Rav Yosef teaches the
discussion. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי המלווה את חבירו בעדים אינו
צריך לפורעו בעדים, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav Assi: hamalveh et chaveiro
b'eidim eino tzarich l'poro b'eidim, that actually the initial statement was that
even the first statement was—not before you get to Shmuel, that you
don't have to pay back with witnesses. ואם אמר, V'im amar, but
if he explicitly stipulated אל תפרעני אלא בעדים, al tifreini ela b'eidim,
you must pay back with witnesses present, then צריך לפורעו בעדים. tzarich
l'poro b'eidim. You have to do it with witnesses, and again presumably
it means not just it has to be paid back, but witnesses
have to be produced to prove it. So according to this, everybody
agrees that if you don't stipulate, you're believed to have said you
paid back. But if you stipulate, then of course you have to
pay back with witnesses—you have to produce the witnesses. כי אמרתי קמיה
דשמואל, Ki amrisi kamei d'Shmuel, so when I said this to Shmuel,
אמר לי יכול לומר לו פרעתיך בפני פלוני ופלוני והלכו להם למדינת
הים. amar li, yachol lomar lo: paraticha bifnei ploni u'ploni v'halchu lahem
limdinat hayam. That Shmuel says maybe if he stipulates you have to
pay back with witnesses, you do have to pay back with witnesses,
but you don't have to produce the witnesses to prove it. You
can basically say, 'Sure, I paid you back with witnesses and they're
not here anymore.' Okay, so for Shmuel, it pretty much—unless you're really
explicit and you say, 'Don't pay me back without witnesses and you're
not believed to claim you paid me back until you can produce
the witnesses', unless you sort of spell all that out, according to
Shmuel, any condition—fine, it's just a condition of how it has to
be paid, but not how it has to be proved. So let's
see what the Mishnah indicates. תנן, Tnan, we learned in our Mishnah:
מנה לי בידך אמר לו הן, amar lo hen. yes. אמר לו
אל תנהו לי אלא בעדים, Amar lo: al tneyhu li ela b'eidim,
this is our Mishnah, only pay me back with witnesses. אל תנהו
לי אלא בפני שני עדים. Al tneyhu li ela bifnei shnei eidim.
למחר אמר לו תנהו לי, L'machar amar lo tneyhu li, give it
to me, and he says נתתי לך, nasati lach, I gave it
to you, חייב מפני שצריך ליתן לו בעדים, chayav mipnei shetzarich litein
lo b'eidim, you have to give it to him with witnesses. And
presumably what that means is—is that he's even—if he can't prove it,
he's חייב. chayav. Presumably, even if he said, 'I gave it to
you in front of witnesses and they're no longer here', the Mishnah
sounds like 'tough luck buddy', 'if you can't produce the witnesses'. That's
a simple sense of the Mishnah. If I said only pay back
with witnesses and you can't produce them, you're חייב. chayav. So that
seems to go against Shmuel. Shmuel says you don't have to actually
produce them. So תיובתא דשמואל, tyuvta d'Shmuel, it's a contradiction to Shmuel.
אמר לך שמואל, Amar lach Shmuel, Shmuel would say to you: תנאי
היא, Tannai hi, you know what? It's true. That Mishnah goes against
me. That Mishnah assumes you have to produce them. I don't think
you have to produce them. But it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim.
דתניא, D'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא. braitah. בעדים הלוויתיך, be'edim hivitisicha,
if I say I lent you money with witnesses, בעדים פרע לי,
be'edim para'li, and therefore I expect you to pay me back with
witnesses, so או יתן או יביא ראיה שנתתי. o yiten o yavi
ra'aya she-nasati. So therefore in that case, so if I make it
clear that you have to pay me with witnesses, then you either
pay me now or bring evidence that you paid me back, meaning
that's the idea that you have to produce the witnesses. If I
say pay me with witnesses, they have to be produced. That's the
idea of our משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna said, if you said
you paid me, you're not believed. You have to produce those witnesses
as I demanded that there be witnesses. But רבי יהודה בן בתירה
Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira אומר, omer, now רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira says like שמואל Shmuel says. יכול לומר לו yachol
lomar lo פרעתיך בפני פלוני ופלוני והלכו להם למדינת הים. paraticha bifnei
ploni u-ploni ve-halchu lahem limdinat hayam. No, I paid you and they
went away. So basically here you have it's a debate of תנאים
tana'im and it's a debate of אמוראים amora'im whether if I say
pay me back with witnesses, does
that mean the witnesses have to be present at the time of
paying only? That's how שמואל Shmuel reads
it in a very narrow sense, but then you can claim later
that they were there and they went away. Or does it mean
and what we would all assume it means, no, no, no, you
have to produce the witnesses if you want to actually be believed,
and that's the assumption our משנה mishna makes. Okay, but what's the
point of even allowing that? Because why would you make the original
demand if somebody can just say they went they went away? Yeah,
I agree. Like you might, you know, I mean that's presumably the
logic. Why else would you make this stipulation if the claim could
just, I mean the point is is that, you know, it's harder
to make that claim. You don't, you know, you don't look people
suspect you when you're saying things like that and they say okay,
who are they? Let me tell me their names. We'll let's try
to go run after and get them, you know what I mean?
It does create certain pressures, but it's not, but yes, it's clearly
the logic is that if I'm demanding witnesses, I mean I want
them to be able to, I mean we need them to testify.
So let's just finish up to the two dots here. פרך רב
אחא. parach rav acha. רב אחא rav acha asked. Now by the
way, there's a תוספות tosafot that says whenever it says פרך רב
אחא, parach rav acha, it is referring to the רב אחא rav
acha גאון ga'on מיסד השאילתות meyased ha-she'iltot who and this is really
like a later insertion in the גמרא, gemara, this was not actually
initially part of the גמרא. gemara. There's a תוספות tosafot that discusses
פרך רב אחא. parach rav acha. פרך רב אחא: parach rav acha:
ממאי דבשעת הלואה קאי? mimai de-bish'at halva'ah ka'i? How do you know
when I say pay me up or, you know, either, you know,
he says I lent you with money pay me back with money—I
said pay me with money I meant with witnesses—anyway you have to
pay me back with witnesses. Who says that transaction in that ברייתא
baraita was talking about what was said at the time of the
loan? דילמא בשעת תביעה קאי? dilma bish'at tviah ka'i? Maybe it was
talking about what was at the time of when the money was
being demanded? והכי קאמר ליה, ve-hachi ka'amar leh, לאו בעדים הלוויתיך? lav
be'edim hivitisicha? Did I not lend you with witnesses? בעדים היה לך
לפורעני. be'edim haya lecha le-porani. So meaning the ברייתא baraita doesn't when
the ברייתא baraita says you have to pay me back with witnesses
and שמואל Shmuel said ah there's a debate whether that means you
have to actually produce the witnesses. רב אחא rav acha here is
saying the ברייתא baraita wasn't clear that that stipulation was made at
the type of the loan. It might be happening that at the
loan no stipulation was made and later the guy is saying why
aren't you paying me back with witnesses? When I lent you I
lent you with witnesses, but not that he actually ever stipulated. Okay,
and in that case where it wasn't stipulating, they're debating whether you
have to produce witnesses. אבל בשעת הלואה, aval bish'at halva'ah, I could
claim in that ברייתא baraita that if the stipulation was explicit at
the time of the loan, דברי הכל חייב, divrei ha-kol chayav, okay
maybe everybody would say you're חייב. chayav. And the גמרא gemara doesn't
have an answer. So שמואל Shmuel has this ברייתא baraita that says
look in this ברייתא baraita there's a debate if you have to
produce witnesses and what and therefore that's the side that says you
don't have to is my side. And now the גמרא gemara is
saying maybe that ברייתא baraita was only talking about when nothing was
stipulated at the time, but maybe if something is stipulated at the
time maybe everybody agrees you have to produce witnesses. All right so
we're still left as open-ended. שמואל Shmuel says you don't have to
produce witnesses, they you might have to claim that they were there
but you don't have to produce them.
And the סתם stam understanding is if you stipulated that there need
to be witnesses it means they need to be produced. Okay let's
just again just wrap up, I'm sorry taking a few more minutes,
but let's just wrap up. Okay. אמר רב פפא, amar rav pappa,
so
said רב פפא משמיה דרבא, rav pappa mishmeih de-rava הלכתא hilchata is,
המלווה חברו בעדים צריך לפורעו בעדים. ha-malveh chaveiro be'edim tzarich le-for'o be'edim.
Yes, if there were witnesses then there at the time then you
have to pay back with witnesses. That's the most demanding of the
positions. רב פפא rav pappa משמיה דרבא mishmeih de-rava, אמר, amar, המלווה
חברו בעדים אין צריך לפורעו בעדים. ha-malveh chaveiro be'edim ein tzarich le-for'o
be'edim. No, no, no, if there was no stipulation then you don't
have to pay back with witnesses. That's generally the assumed פסק psak
throughout ש"ס. shas. But if you lend even if there were witnesses
at the time of the lending without any stipulation you don't need
to produce witnesses. But how about the other point which was the
big debate? ואם אמר אל תפרעני אלא בעדים, ve-im amar al tifre'ni
ela be'edim, don't pay me without witnesses, צריך לפורעו בעדים, tzarich le-for'o
be'edim, then you need obviously. ואם אמר לו פרעתיך בפני פלוני ופלוני
והלכו להם למדינת הים, ve-im amar lo paraticha bifnei ploni u-ploni ve-halchu
lahem limdinat hayam, now this question שמואל's Shmuel claim that you can
say there were witnesses but I'm not going to produce them, then
our version is נאמן, ne'eman, you're believed, ruling like שמואל, Shmuel, very,
very lenient. But if you look at the side, the side says
the רמב״ם's Rambam גרסא girsa is אינו נאמן. eino ne'eman. So exactly,
we, you know, if Mike was here he'd be so excited, we're
actually ruling, but then the key question, how do we rule
depends what גרסא girsa you have. Certainly the thrust of the גמרא
Gemara and the logic as David says, if the guy says, don't
pay me back except with witnesses, presumably you've got to produce the
witnesses, it's not enough to claim that they were there, okay? And
certainly that's the evidence, the פשט peshat of our משנה. mishna. But
שמואל Shmuel says you don't have to produce them, and it's not
clear in the end how the גמרא Gemara rules on that point.
Okay, we will end with...